Guide to the Stephanie Strickland Papers, 1955-2016 RL.01262
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stephanie Strickland papers
1955-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Strickland, Stephanie
RL.01262
30.5 Linear Feet
Stephanie Strickland is a poet and born-digital writer whose works range from paper to interactive websites. She also teaches and serves on the board of the Electronic Literature Organization. Her papers include journals and anthologies featuring Strickland's poetry; TechnoPoetry Festival materials; schoolwork, college, and graduate papers; posters and programs from events; proofs and drafts of her writings; and audio recordings.
5550 Physical items; 180.3 gigabytes
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Stephanie Strickland Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009, 2012, 2015, 2017, and 2020.
Biographical Note
Stephanie Strickland is a poet and digital writer whose works range from paper to interactive websites. She studied at Harvard, Sarah Lawrence College, and Pratt Institute. She also teaches and serves on the board of the Electronic Literature Organization.
Strickland's books are among the first examples of printed text being published in conjunction with electronic media. During her career, Strickland's work has included interactive poetry CDs; hypertext disks and web environments; poems in printed journals and anthologies; and articles about literature and cyberspace.
Collection Overview
The Stephanie Strickland Papers include printed journals and anthologies featuring Strickland's poetry, programs and posters from Strickland's publications and performances; school materials from high school to graduate school; articles and anthologies; electronic media (removed); videotapes; and other miscellaneous materials. There are source materials from works such as Zone: Zero, True North, Sand Soot, and Vniverse; conference programs; journals; and gallery catalogs and other sources used in her work, as well as files, proofs, and drafts from Strickland's V: Vniverse, True North, Zone: Zero, Red Virgin, Give the Body Back, V: WaveSon.nets / Losing L'una, Dragon Logic and other Strickland poems, essays, and compilations. There is a small amount of print correspondence and event material. There is a larger amount of electronic correspondence. Electronic media has been separated from the accession and housed on Duke's electronic records server but has been described in this collection guide.There are several VHS and cassette recordings of interviews with Stephanie Strickland and related to her work.
Arrangement note
Collection is arranged into series: Correspondence, which includes email captures; Writings, including Strickland's projects, collaborations, essays, publications, and writings by others; Education and Academia; Miscellany; Audiovisual; and Unprocessed Additions.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Conditions Governing Access
Some materials may require preservation copies be created before use.
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of this collection are unprocessed (additions 2020-0043 and 2020-007) and require additional arrangement, description, and/or screening. Contact research services for more information.
CD-ROMs; Poetry, Modern -- 21st century; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century; Hypertext poetry; Electronic Literature Organization; Strickland, Stephanie
- Correspondence, 1984-2015
  - Assorted, 1984-2001 (Box 5)
  - Joe Tabbi, re: True North, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Cynthia Lawson, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
  - Letters from Kate Hayles to Howard Foundation, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Email Correspondence, 2001-2018
    Scope and Contents note
    Messages in this subseries were largely captured from Strickland's email account, with some messages transferred from email accounts belonging to Cynthia Lawson Jaramillo. Primary correspondents include Cynthia Lawson Jaramillo, Nick Montfort, and Ian Hatcher. The messages to and from these individuals are often with regard to Strickland's collaborations with them each: slippingglimpse and Vniverse (Lawson); Sea and Spar Between (Montfort); Vniverse iPad app (Hatcher). Other frequent correspondents include Jaishree Odin, Joergen Schaefer, Marjorie Luesebrink, and Judy Malloy. Other works by Strickland are discussed as well, including Sand and Soot, V, and Zone: Zero. Additional topics discussed include Strickland's work with the Electronic Literature Organization, pending publications in Digital Humanities Quarterly and the Electronic Literature Collection, workshops and speaking engagements.
    Access Restrictions
    Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
    - Capture of March 2010, 2005-2010; Approximately 250 email messages; approximately 70 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
      Consists of email messages exported from Strickland's email account as EML files. Messages normalized to MBOX format and arranged as received in four directories: correspondence with Cynthia Lawson Jaramillo regarding Vniverse, messages relating to slippingglimpse, messages related to V, and miscellaneous messages.
    - Capture of August 2010, 2001-2010; Approximately 1000 email messages; approximately 70 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
      Consists of messages between Strickland and Cynthia Lawson Jaramillo captured from Lawson Jaramillo's New York University-associated and personal email accounts. Messages are aggregated in two MBOX files, one each corresponding to the New York University and personal accounts. A copy of each MBOX file has been normalized to EML.
    - Capture of January 2011, 2010-2011; Approximately 450 email messages; 15 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
      Consists of messages harvested from Strickland's email account in EML format. A copy has been migrated to MBOX.
    - Capture of January 2012, 2006-2012; Approximately 650 email messages; 30 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
    - Capture of January 2013, 2012-2013; Approximately 450 email messages; 30 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
    - Capture of January 2014, 2013-2014; Approximately 1000 email messages; 300 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
    - Capture of February 2015, 2012-2015; Approximately 700 email messages; 250 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
    - Capture of 2016, 2009-2016; Approximately 300 email messages; 200 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
      Scope and Contents
      Email messages harvested from Strickland's email account in EML format. A copy has been migrated to MBOX.
    - Capture of 2017, 2014-2017; Approximately 300 email messages; 100 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
    - Capture of 2018, 2017-2018; 125 email messages; approximately 40 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01262-SET-0001)
      Email harvested from Strickland's email account in MBOX format. A copy has been migrated to EML format.
- Writings, 1970s-2010s
  - Projects
    - True North
      - True North proof and other materials, undated (Box 5)
      - So Far From Home... (early version of True North), undated (Box 5)
      - Notebooks, 1986 and undated (Box 5)
      - Drafts, 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Drafts, from RV binder, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Draft, 1987 (early version with plans) (Box 5)
      - Variant, July 1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Organization notes and spec sheets (Box 5)
      - True North workbook and links (Box 10)
      - NEH Seminar and True North, 1995-1997 (2 folders), 2 folders (Box 10)
      - True North materials (Box 10)
      - True North, 1997; Disk images derived from two floppy disks. (Box 20)
    - V: Vniverse
      - Folder of V: Vniverse source materials; visual sources and inspiration; notes and correspondence from 2000 (Box 5)
      - V: Vniverse correspondence and initial notes (Box 5)
      - V: Vniverse constellations; some materials about generative version (Box 5)
      - Vniverse installation plans: never executed (Box 5)
      - Vniverse working materials (Box 10)
      - Vniverse digital materials, Production digital files captured from Strickland and Cynthia Lawson Jaramillo's website. Previous versions transferred by Strickland and Lawson separately. Approximately 79 megabytes.
        Includes web files needed to run Vniverse as it existed online in 2010. Also includes previous versions and drafts dating from a 2001 beta version and versions from 2003, 2007, and 2009. Files run on modern computing platforms in contemporary web browsers with Shockwave installed.
    - Give the Body Back
      - Milk in Glass Bottles draft (early version of Give the Body Back) (Box 4)
      - Milk in Glass Bottles draft (Box 4)
      - The Fault of the Body draft with edits (Box 4)
      - The Fault of the Body MFA thesis (Box 4)
      - Living on Air (early version of Give the Body Back) (Box 4)
      - Galleys, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Give the Body Back early materials, reactions; MFA thesis evaluation (Box 4)
    - V: WaveSon.nets / Losing L'una
      - V: Wave Son.nets/Losing L'una proofs, 2002 (Box 5)
      - V: Wave Son.nets/Losing L'una third proof, 2002 (Box 5)
      - WaveSon.nets/MacDowell long scroll printouts, August 12 and 15, 1997 (Box 4)
      - WaveSon.nets/MacDowell printouts, August 28, 1997 (Box 4)
      - The Woman Who Cannot Do Without (early L'una draft) (Box 4)
      - Saying Simone/Simone Says (early L'una draft) (Box 4)
      - Saying Simone (early Losing L'una), April-June 1997 (Box 4)
      - V: Wave Son.nets/Losing L'una proofs; Reader's Report and other reviews and interviews (Box 4)
      - proofs and design questions (Box 18)
    - The Red Virgin: A Poem of Simone Weil (Box 17)
      - Red Virgin quote sources, in order (Box 4)
      - The Red Virgin commentary and reviews (Box 4)
      - Notes, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
      - The Simone Weil Poem draft with edits, 1985 (Box 4)
      - The Simone Weil Poem bound draft, 1985 (Box 4)
      - The Only Rival: Simone Weil drafts, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - The Truth Which Bites: Simone Weil draft and correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 4)
      - The Red Virgin: A Poem of Simone Weil (bound version), 1993 (Box 4)
    - Zone: Zero
      - Zone: Zero proof, 2007 (Box 4)
      - Zone: Zero final proof, 2007 (Box 4)
      - Zero: Zero source and marketing materials (Box 10)
    - Untitled draft about apples (Box 4)
    - Flame-Retention Head draft (Box 4)
    - There is a Woman in a Conical Hat
      - Draft, December 16, 1997 (Box 9)
      - Draft, July 6, 1998 (Box 9)
      - Draft, June 1999 (Box 9)
      - Drafts (Box 9)
    - "V": includes Losing L'una and There is a Woman in a Conical Hat (Box 9)
    - Various drafts, 2 folders (Box 9)
      Including True North and V: WaveSon.nets/Losing L'una variations, as well as student work.
    - Various drafts from binder (Box 9)
    - Conversation Between Women draft (Box 9)
    - The Birds draft (Box 9)
    - Walls That Were a Garden (Box 10)
    - To Be Here as Stone Is
      - To Be Here as Stone Is drafts (Box 4)
      - Link structure for To Be Here as Stone Is (Box 10)
      - To Be Here as Stone Is digital files, 1999-2002, Digital files extracted from USB thumb drive. Approximately 1 megabyte.
        Digital files comprise two versions of the web-based work, one each optimized for Microsoft Internet Explorer and Netscape Navigator. Both versions will run in modern web browsers.
    - Errand Upon Which We Came
      - Errand Upon Which We Came (Box 10)
      - Errand Upon Which We Came digital files, 1999-2000; Disk image and access copies derived from optical disc. Approximately 26 megabytes. Additional files extracted from USB thumb drive. Approximately 11 megabytes.
        Two versions of files making up Errand Upon Which We Came from optical disc. Additional three copies from USB thumb drive. Each version features slight differences in the arrangement of component files, though that may not affect the performance of the work. Files can be viewed in a web browser with Shockwave and Flash installed.
      - Errand Upon Which We Came web archive
    - Ballad of Sand and Harry Soot
      - Ballad of Sand and Harry Soot (Box 10)
      - Sand Soot materials (Box 10)
      - Ballad of Sand and Harry Soot digital files, 1999-2001, Digital files extracted from USB thumb drive. Approximately 1 megabyte.
        Digital files comprise a working version of the web-based work. Files will render in modern web browsers.
    - Slippingglimpse
      - Source materials for slippingglimpse (Box 10)
      - slippingglimpse digital materials, Files captured from Strickland and Cynthia Lawson Jaramillo's website. Approximately 434 megabytes.
        Includes digital files needed to run slippingglimpse as it existed online in 2010. Files are compatible with multiple computing platforms and contemporary web browsers with Shockwave installed. Also included is a video file of the work on a loop.
    - Dragon Logic
      - Notebook 1, Summer 2006 (Box 11)
        Mostly handwritten notes. Original title The Age of Sciwince.
      - Notebook 2, Summer 2006 (Box 11)
        Mostly handwritten notes.
      - Early Printouts, 2006; 2 folders (Box 11)
        Folder 1 contains 1-89 and folder 2 contains 90-171. Early printouts of the transcriptions.
      - Draft, September 2006, 2 folders (Box 11)
        Folder 1 contains 1-89 and folder 2 contains 90-170. Folder 1 also contains pink ordering sheets.
      - 2006 Draft 1 (Box 11)
      - 2006 Draft 2 (Box 11)
      - Summer 2007 Draft (Box 13)
        With annotations by Denise Duhamel.
      - Summer 2007 Reordered Draft (Box 13)
        Manuscript draft reordered to Denise Duhamel's suggestion.
      - Draft, 2007 Aug. 10 (Box 13)
      - Draft, 2007 Aug. 13 (Box 13)
      - Draft, 2010[?] (Box 13)
      - Draft, 2010 Dec. (Box 13)
      - Late Version, undated (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous Version Fragments (Box 13)
      - Advance Reader's Copy (Box 17)
        &NOW Proposal
      - Dragons Green & Blue proof, 2012 Dec. 30 (Box 17)
      - Dragon Logic final proof, 2013 Apr. 4 (Box 17)
      - Huracan's Harp, 2008 (Box 17)
      - Dragon Logic Sources (brown folder) (Box 18)
        conference papers, magazine articles, exhibits
      - Dragon Logic Sources (blue folder) (Box 18)
        many Laetus in Praesens
      - Early Huracan's Harp notes, 2010 (Box 18)
        PenTab notebook
    - Jaishree K. Odin interview versions about True North and V, 2002 (Box 10)
    - AnA drafts, 2001-2003, Digital files extracted from USB thumb drive. Approximately 239 megabytes.
      Digital files include notes and draft versions of AnA and AnaDusk, a collaboration between Strickland and M.D. Coverley. Files will run in contemporary web browsers in Windows and Macintosh platforms.
    - The Iowa Review Web, 9.1, 2006-2007; Digital files extracted from USB thumb drive. Approximately 7 megabytes.
    - Electronic literature collection, Vol. 2, 2011 February; Disk image created from USB. (Box 20)
    - Storyspace software, 1993-1995; Disk images derived from four floppy disks. (Box 20)
  - Journals and Publications
    - Controlled Burn 1, Winter 1995 (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Review 12.1, Spring 2000 (Box 1)
    - Indiana Review 27.1, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Extended Outlooks: The Iowa Review Collection of Contemporary Women Writers, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Barrow Street 2.1, Fall 1999 (Box 1)
    - Tendril: A Poetry Magazine 13, Summer 1982 (Box 1)
    - Tendril: A Poetry Magazine 19-20 (Box 1)
    - Prairie Schooner, 1985 (2), 1987, 1990, and 1994 (Box 1)
    - West Branch 7-8, 1980 (Box 1)
    - West Branch 14, 1984 (Box 1)
    - West Branch 26, 1990 (Box 1)
    - American Letters and Commentary 5, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Voices in Italian Americana, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Ironwood 16, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Ironwood 23, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Ironwood 25, 1985 (Box 1)
    - The Agni Review 14 and 20 (Box 1)
    - Chain 5, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Ploughshares 27.1, Spring 2001 (Box 1)
    - The Paris Review 132, Fall 1994 (Box 1)
    - Tin Fish 3, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Big Allis 8, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Salt Hill 6, 1998 (Box 1)
    - State Street Reader, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Southern Poetry Review, Spring 1986 (Box 1)
    - Soundings East 8.2, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Pequod 14, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Kenyon Review 13.3, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Kenyon Review 15.4, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kenyon Review 17.1, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Poets and Writers, 2001 (Box 1)
      Includes an article on literature and cyberspace.
    - Iris: A Journal About Women 14, 1985 (Box 1)
    - America, 15 June 1991 (Box 1)
    - The Mad Hatter's Review (online journal), 4 May 2008 (Box 1)
    - Poetry New York 12, Spring 2001 (Box 1)
    - Audio CD: Conversing with Mystery: Poetry for Transition and Loss (Box 1)
    - The Chowder Review 20/21, Summer 1985 (Box 2)
    - Seneca Review 30.2, Fall 2000 (Box 2)
    - Pomegranate Series 4, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Ploughshares 10.1, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Iowa Review 9.3, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Iowa Review 12.2-3, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Poets on Nourishment 9.1, Winter 1985 (Box 2)
    - TechnoPoetry Festival, 2001-2003
      - TechnoPoetry Festival materials, 2002 (Box 10)
      - Student work from Georgia Institute of Technology's TechnoPoetry Festival, 2002 (Box 12)
      - Conference Proceedings Digital Materials, 4608 Megabytes; Disk images derived from two optical discs. Approximately 4.5 gigabytes.
        Digital files distributed after the conference on both compact and digital versatile disc. Because of storage limits, each differs slightly in what is stored. On the compact disc, audio recordings of artists talks, video recordings of some talks, and descriptions of installations are included. The larger capacity disc includes video recordings of the artists talks, as well as video recordings of exhibits and installations. Both discs were created with Windows and Macintosh platforms in mind, but require Shockwave players in order to render content.
      - Symposia and Artists Talks Transcripts, Disk images derived from two 3.5" floppy disks and a TAR archive file. Approximately 4 megabytes.
      - TechnoPoetry Festival Mixed Media Digital Materials, Disk images derived from two external hard drives. Approximately 132 gigabytes. Logical files extracted from a failing third external hard drive. Approximately 56 gigabytes.
        Digital files fall mainly into three categories related to the TechnoPoetry Festival--materials related to the artists who spoke or otherwise participated at the festival, materials related to the creation of the conference proceedings media, and materials related to the Festival's web presence. Materials pertaining to the artists include video of some exhibitions, video of artists' talks, video recordings (non-interactive) of electronic literature pieces, interactive renderings of electronic literature, and other related desktop pddublishing and office files.
        Materials related to the conference proceedings media include the recordings from artists' talks and sessions as well as recordings of some artists' installations. Material may partially duplicate that found on the conference proceedings media (RL01262-OP-0011 and RL01262-OP-0018), though may be easier to navigate in this structure.
        Materials related to the festival's web presence include HTML and media files that were once hosted on the live web. As of 2015, the live version of the website is no longer online.
      - Artists Talks digital materials
    - Poet Lore 90.3, Fall 1995 (Box 2)
    - Slant: A Journal of Poetry, Summer 1987 (Box 2)
    - Chelsea 70/71, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Porch 4.1, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Calyx, February 1980 (Box 2)
    - Ekphrasis 1.2, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Verse and Universe: Poems About Science and Mathematics, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Voices from the River, 1990 (Box 2)
    - American Letters and Commentary 10, 1998 (Box 2)
    - American Letters and Commentary 12, 2000 (Box 2)
    - American Letters and Commentary 13, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Notre Dame Review 11, Winter 2001 (Box 2)
    - Notre Dame Review 12, Summer 2001 (Box 2)
    - Jubilat 4, 2002 (Box 2)
    - New World Poetry Bi-Monthly, December 2003 (Box 2)
    - Synaesthetic 2 (Box 2)
    - The Epistolary Form and the Letter as Artifact 17, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Isotope 4.1, 2006 (Box 2)
      Includes an article on poetry and science.
    - Calapooya Collage 12, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Calapooya Collage 17, 1993 (Box 2)
    - NC 2, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Songs for Our Voices, 1993 (Box 2)
    - The Muse Strikes Back, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Open Door (Poet Love Anthology), 1999 (Box 2)
    - The Little Magazine 16, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Best of Prairie Schooner, 2001 (Box 2)
    - How Shall We Tell Each Other of the Past? The Life and Writings of Muriel Rukeyser, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Search And You Will Find, 1998 (Box 2)
    - The Breast: An Anthology, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Divided Again: Poems About Designing People, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Columbia Poetry Review 18, Spring 2005 (Box 3)
    - Strange Attractors: Poems of Love and Mathematics, 2008 (Box 3)
    - Atomic Ghost: Poets Respond to the Nuclear Age, 1995 (Box 3)
    - New Poetry: The Extraordinary Tide by American Women, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Lit 2, Winter 2000 (Box 3)
    - The American Voice 12, Fall 1988 (Box 3)
    - The American Voice 21, Winter 1990 (Box 3)
    - In a Field of Words: A Creative Writing Text, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Conditions 7, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Fence 2.1, 1999 (Box 3)
    - New Virginia Review 6, 1988 (Box 3)
    - New Virginia Review 9.1, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Bellingham Review 19.1, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Notre Dame Review 2, Summer 1996 (Box 3)
    - Many Mountains Moving 8.1, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
    - Lumina, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Meridian 6, Fall 2000 (Box 3)
    - Mid-American Review 23.1, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Looking for Home: Women Writing About Exile, 1990 (Box 3)
    - The Measured Word: On Poetry and Science, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Image 23, Summer 1999 (Box 3)
    - Image 31, Summer 2001 (Box 3)
    - Doubletake 2.4, Fall 1996 (Box 3)
    - Croton Review 7, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Black Buzzard Review 1, 1988 (Box 3)
    - 5:AM, Winter 1988 (Box 3)
    - Vlak 1.1, 2010 (Box 14)
    - Notre Dame review: The First Ten Years, 2009 (Box 14)
    - Rhythm of Structure, 2011 (Box 14)
    - Dandelion Mapping 37.1, 2011 (Box 14)
    - Barrow Street, 2011-2012 (Box 14)
    - Chicago Review 56:2/3, 2011 (Box 14)
    - Dandelion v.36, Chapter 1&2 (Box 14)
    - Zoland Poetry, no. 5, 2011 (Box 14)
    - Western Humanities Review, v.65 no.2, Summer 2012 (Box 14)
    - American Book Review v.32 no.6, 2011 (Box 14)
    - A chapter written in: A Broken Thing, 2011 (Box 14)
    - Beyond This Silence chapbook, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Dandelion Magazine: The Mapping Issue, 37.1 (Box 12)
    - Ironwood 25, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Western Humanities Review 65.2, Summer 2011 (Box 12)
    - 1913 A Journal of Forms 3, 2009 (Box 12)
    - Volt, 2008-2009 (Box 12)
    - Experimental Literary Education, 2009 (Box 12)
    - The Measured Word, edited by Kurt Brown (Box 12)
    - WSQ: Technologies, 2009 (Box 12)
    - P-Queue, 2009 (Box 12)
    - American Letters & Commentary: Special Feature: collaborations, 2008 (Box 12)
    - Prairie Schooner, 1988 (Box 12)
    - The Georgia Review, 1998 (Box 12)
    - Bird Dog 9, 2008 (Box 12)
    - Gargoyle 35, 1988 (Box 12)
    - court green 2, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Salt Hill 6, 1998 (Box 12)
    - Grand Street, 2002 (Box 12)
    - Small Press, Spring 1994 (Box 6)